A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 3255-6261 FA739B
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 3255-6261
1936-2005
1950s-1990s
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA739B
60.28 Cubic Feet Document boxes 145-281.
Other Finding Aids
For descriptions of Ford Foundation Catalogued Reports, please refer to the following finding aids (arranged by Report Number):
FA739A Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 1-3254
FA739C Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 6262-9286
FA739D Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 9287-11774
FA739E Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 11775-13948
FA739F Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 13949-17726
FA739G Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 17727-19980
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Catalogued Reports are open for research with select reports restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
The Catalogued Reports are arranged numerically by an arbitrary call number assigned during cataloging, from 1 to approximately 20,000.
Scope and Contents
The Ford Foundation’s Catalogued Reports collection includes policy and programming documents, program evaluations, and periodic program status reports produced by Foundation officers and staff, as well as consultants and grantees. Some published material produced by Ford Foundation grants is also included in the collection. The collection also includes some of the Ford Foundation’s own publications, such as the Annual Reports and newsletters.
Biographical / Historical
In the early 1970s, the Ford Foundation’s archives staff began to identify and catalog individual reports, policy and programming documents, and program evaluations in an effort to create an internal lending-library of useful documents. Many of the Catalogued Reports were physically culled from the former Foundation officers’ and staff’s archival collections of ‘office files’. When those collections of ‘office files’ were later processed, and finding aids created, an appendix of “Reports Removed” (or, Reports Transferred”) was added to the finding aids.
By 1977 the collection included more than 3,500 reports, and by 1979 some 5,000 reports had been cataloged.
Duplicated copies of the reports were also created on microfiche, and later microfilm.
Ford Foundation
- Preventive programs for mothers and infants: The child survival program in context (Reports 003255), 1984 (Box 144)
  Program Name
  United States and International Affairs Program/Rural Poverty and Resources
  Extent
  57 p.
  Child care; Medical care
- Giving is good business (Reports 003256), 1956 (Box 144)
  Abstract/Summary
  "Address ... before the Chamber of Commerce of Greater Philadelphia, Thursday, May 10, 1956." --p.1.
  Board of Trustees
  13 p.
  Public-private sector cooperation; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- Finance; Humanitarianism; Philanthropy; Ford Foundation. Board of Trustees
- Talk by Dean Donald K. David on his European trip (Reports 003257), 1954 (Box 144)
  9 p.
  Business education -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Europe; Economics -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Europe; Executives -- Training of -- Europe; Business schools -- Europe; Universities and colleges -- Europe; Education, Higher -- Europe; Ford Foundation. Board of Trustees
- Analysis of ministerial projects and programs for 1976 - 1980, and revised projections for 1977 - 1981 (Reports 003258) (Box 144)
  International Division/Middle East and Africa
  164 p.: principally tables, charts: 28 cm.
  Ford Foundation Series
  Analysis of ministerial projects and programs for 1976-1980, and revised projections for 1977-1981: Volume I, Financial analysis.
  Finance, Public -- Bahrain -- Statistics; National income -- Bahrain -- Statistics; Economics -- Research -- Bahrain; Bahrain. Wizarat al-Maliyah wa-al-Iqtisad al-Watani. Idarat al-Taqyim wa-al-Buhuth al-Iqtisadiah
- Analysis of ministerial projects and programs for 1976 - 1980, and revised projections for 1977 - 1981 (Reports 003259) (Box 144)
  159 p.: principally tables: 28 cm.
  Analysis of ministerial projects and programs for 1976 - 1980, and revised projections for 1977 - 1981: Volume II, Manpower analysis.
  Finance, Public -- Bahrain -- Statistics; Economics -- Research -- Bahrain; Manpower -- Bahrain -- Statistics; Labor supply -- Bahrain -- Statistics; Bahrain. Wizarat al-Maliyah wa-al-Iqtisad al-Watani. Idarat al-Taqyim wa-al-Buhuth al-Iqtisadiah
- Analysis of ministerial projects and programs for 1976 - 1980, and revised projections for 1977 - 1981 (Reports 003260) (Box 145)
  86 p.: principally tables: 28 cm.
  Analysis of ministerial projects and programs for 1976-1980, and revised projections for 1977-1981: Volume III, Administrative Analysis.
  Finance, Public -- Bahrain -- Statistics; Finance, Public Bahrain -- Administration; National income -- Bahrain -- Statistics; Economics -- Research -- Bahrain; Bahrain. Wizarat al-Maliyah wa-al-Iqtisad al-Watani. Idarat al-Taqyim wa-al-Buhuth al-Iqtisadiah
- Urban and regional development in Chile: a case study of innovative planning (Reports 003261), 1969 (Box 145)
  International Division/Latin America and the Caribbean
  [xv], 251p.: tables
  City planning -- Chile -- Case studies; City planning -- Chile; Regional planning -- Chile -- Case studies; Urbanization -- Chile -- Case studies; Ford Foundation. Field Office Santiago; Ford Foundation. Latin America and the Caribbean
- The Ford Foundation and Foundation-supported activities in India: summary of grants from 1951 to July 15 (Reports 003262), 1963 (Box 145)
  Title sufficient as abstract.
  Overseas Division/South and Southeast Asia
  24 p.
  Philanthropy -- India; Ford Foundation India
- The relation of U.S. resource base grants to overseas development (Reports 003263), 1969 (Box 145)
  19 p. + attachment: 28 cm.
  Economic assistance -- Developing countries; Technical assistance -- Developing countries; Charity organization -- Developing countries; Philanthropy -- Developing countries
- Draft of report on program five to be included in president's report to trustees (Reports 003264), 1952 (Box 145)
  10 p.
  Psychology -- Study and teaching (Graduate) -- United States; Social sciences -- Study and teaching (Graduate) -- United States; Behavioral scientists -- Training of; Education (Graduate) -- United States; Ford Foundation. Board of Trustees
- Memorandum on Foundation group going to Indonesia and Burma 1952? (Reports 003265) (Box 145)
  [10] leaves -- 28 cm.
  Philanthropy -- Indonesia; Philanthropy -- Burma; Philanthropy -- Middle East; Endowments -- Indonesia; Endowments -- Burma; Endowments -- Middle East; Ford Foundation
- Study of education in Latin America (Reports 003266), 1970 (Box 145)
  Memo to ID representatives, dated January 21, 1970.
  3 p. + attachment
  Education -- Research -- Latin America; Ford Foundation. Latin America and the Caribbean
- The commitment to culture and the arts (Reports 003267), 1963 (Box 145)
  Remarks prepared for the 46th annual meeting of the American Council on Education held in Washington, D.C.
  Humanities & Arts program
  6 p.
  Culture -- Study and teaching -- United States; Arts -- Study and teaching -- United States
- Remarks made at a workshop preliminary to a conference on education, employment, and rural development, The University College, Nairobi, April 22nd (Reports 003268), 1966 (Box 145)
  Conference held at the University College, Nairobi on April 22, 1966.
  Overseas Division/Middle East and Africa
  Related Grant Number
  06600165
  Education -- Africa; Rural development -- Africa
- Studying the presidency: results, needs, and resources (Reports 003269), 1976 (Box 145)
  Public Policy and Social Organization
  Presidents -- Research -- United States; Ford Foundation. Public Policy and Social Organization
- Program for Asia and the Near East (Reports 003270), 1953 (Box 145)
  Overseas Division
  61 p.
  Charity organization -- Asia; Charity organization -- Middle East; Philanthropy -- Asia; Philanthropy -- Middle East; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Planning occupational education and training for development (Reports 003271), 1970 (Box 145)
  International Division/Asia and the Pacific
  07000218
  Related Grantee Name
  The Leland Stanford Junior University
  Related Grant Purpose
  Master's Degree program in educational development for persons from Southeast Asia.
  188 p.
  Economic development -- Effect of education on; Vocational education; The Leland Stanford Junior University
- A brief report on the National Council of Technical Education in Argentina (Reports 003272), 1967 (Box 145)
  10 leaves -- 28 cm.
  Technical education -- Argentina; Vocational education -- Argentina; Manpower -- Argentina; Manpower planning -- Argentina; Manpower policy -- Argentina; Teachers -- Training of -- Argentina
- Notes on manpower development and utilization aspects of a national science and technology policy (Reports 003273), 1971 (Box 145)
  International Division/Latin America and the Caribbean/Asia and the Pacific
  Technical education; Science -- Study and teaching (Higher); Science -- Occupational training
- Innovation, adaptation, and diffusion of reforms in science teaching in Latin America (Reports 003274), 1970 (Box 145)
  Paper at the American Association for the Advancement of Science 137th meeting.
  26 p. -- 28 cm
  Science -- Study and teaching -- Latin America
- Television: a revolutionary new tool in American education (Reports 003275), 1958 (Box 145)
  The Fund for Advancement of Education;Education
  1 v.: var pag.
  Television in education -- United States; Television in higher education -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States; Ford Foundation. Education Program
- Social considerations and the investment process: A report to the Ford Foundation (Reports 003276), 1972 (Box 146)
  Finance/Office of the Vice President
  97 p.
  Public-private sector cooperation; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- Finance; Ford Foundation. Office of the Vice President; Ford Foundation
- Report on the study of communication problems in the public services of Ghana (Reports 003277), 1969 (Box 146)
  06380473
  The Government of Ghana
  Advice on government reforms, re-training of public servants, and assistance of new staff college.
  ix, 25 p.
  Communication in public administration -- Ghana; Public administration -- Ghana; Ford Foundation. Middle East and Africa
- Ghana administrative staff college: a guideline report (Reports 003278), 1968 (Box 146)
  19 p. + attachments: tables, charts
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted from scholarly access.
  Public administration -- Study and teaching -- Ghana; Ghana
- Office of Government Machinery Project: End-of-tour report (Reports 003279), 1971 (Box 146)
  06800473
  44 p.
  Public administration -- Study and teaching -- Ghana; Ford Foundation. Middle East and Africa
- Changing problems of development: a background paper (Reports 003280), 1969 (Box 146)
  Paper for presentation at the FF International Division Conference at Mexico City, December 3-5, 1969. Discussion of the role the Foundation can play in development in a changing climate.
  14 p.
  Economic development -- Developing Countries; Ford Foundation. International Division Asia and the Pacific. India Field Office.
- Note on training for community development projects (Reports 003281), 1952 (Box 146)
  Community development -- India; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Evaluation of the Community Development Program: a contribution of the Ford Foundation (Reports 003282), 1952 (Box 146)
  2 p.
- Problems and issues concerning Vietnam veterans, deserters, and draft-evaders: information paper (Reports 003283), 1974 (Box 146)
  Preliminary study of the effects of the Vietnam War on the lives of those who entered military service and those who became lawbreakers out of opposition to participation.
  59 p. + attachment
  Veterans -- Law and legislation -- United States; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Veterans; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Draft resisters; Ford Foundation. Public Policy and Social Organization
- The university and the creative arts: II (Reports 003284), 1967 (Box 146)
  Speech delivered at the First Annual Fine Arts Festival, Edwardsville, Illinois, April 16, 1967.
  20 p.
  Arts -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Artists -- Training of -- United States; Arts and society -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States; Ford Foundation. Humanities and the Arts
- Why bother about the arts? (Reports 003285), 1977 (Box 146)
  25 p. + attachments: tables
  Arts -- United States -- Finance; Arts and society -- United States; Ford Foundation. Humanities and the Arts
- Dedication: Memorial Plaza, January 21, 1970. (Reports 003286) (Box 146)
  Includes messages by: Douglas Ensminger, Julius Stratton, C. D. Deshmukh, Indira Gandhi, and G. Ramachandran.
  20 p.: ill.
  Human rights -- India; Human rights -- United States; Civil rights -- India; Civil rights -- United States; Nonviolence; Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific
- Investment policies, spending policies, and uncertainty (Reports 003287), 1977 (Box 146)
  Includes an introduction with comments on the paper by Roger Kennedy and a separate paper by Gary L. Bergstrom, "The Ford Foundation Investment & Spending Policy Stimulator."
  49 p. + 6 p. appendices: charts, graphs, tables -- 28 cm.
  Endowments -- Finance -- Planning; Ford Foundation
- The Thana Irrigation Programme and notes on local rural planning for Bangladesh (Reports 003289), 1976 (Box 146)
  46 p.
  Irrigation -- Social aspects; Rural development -- Bangladesh; Irrigation -- Management -- Bangladesh
- A brief report to the chairman of BAI(SS)C (Reports 003290), 1975 (Box 146)
  19 p.
  Fiscal policy -- India; Finance, Public -- India; Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific
- Some notes regarding planning and research in the Philippine agricultural sector (Reports 003291), 1976 (Box 146)
  21 p.
  Agriculture -- Economic aspects -- Philippines; Agriculture -- Research -- Philippines; Agriculture and state -- Philippines; Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific
- Procedures for the selective support of investigation relating to Asia and the Middle East (Reports 003292), 1958 (Box 146)
  International Training and Research
  41 p.
  Charity organization -- Asia; Charity organization -- Middle East; Ford Foundation. International Training and Research
- Training and research potential of Southeast Asia studies in England, with particular reference to Burma (Reports 003293), 1954 (Box 146)
  Foreign study -- England; Area studies -- England; Ford Foundation. International Training and Research
- The Institution Building Project (Reports 003294), 1966 (Box 146)
  International Division/International Relations
  11 p. + attachments
  Educational assistance -- Developing countries; Technical assistance -- Developing countries; Employment in foreign countries -- Developing countries; Ford Foundation. International Relations Program
- Resources and conservation: study for project of the Ford Foundation, July 1952. (Reports 003295) (Box 146)
  Econonmic Development & Adminsitration
  7 p.
  Conservation of natural resources -- United States -- Government policy; Conservation of natural resources -- Law and legislation -- United States; Ford Foundation. Economic Development Administration
- Report from Asia (Reports 003296), 1959 (Box 146)
  Economics -- Research -- Asia; Ford Foundation. South and Southeast Asia
- Toward a universal curriculum (Reports 003297), 1961 (Box 146)
  "Paper read at the annual Conference of Academic Deans, Denver, Colorado, January 11, 1961." --p.1.
  Education
  General education -- United States; Education, Humanistic -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States -- Curricula; Ford Foundation. Education Program
- The Middle East bulletin: Iran (Reports 003298), 1951 (Box 146)
  8 leaves -- 28 cm.
  International relations; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Conference on urbanism, Ford Foundation, October 10-11, 1956: summary and conclusions (Reports 003299) (Box 146)
  26 p.
  Related Conference
  PAPER Conference (1956 Oct. 10-11: New York, N.Y.)
  Urbanization -- Congresses; City planning -- Congresses; Ford Foundation. Economic Development Administration
- A summary: Ford Foundation activities (in) Burma: Report no. 13, July 13 (Reports 003300), 1954 (Box 146)
  Cataloged by D.Merkle;Electronic content available in SharePoint Archives collection
  4 leaves -- 28 cm.
  Ford Foundation in Burma
  Philanthropy -- Burma; Endowments -- Burma; Ford Foundation
- Notes on conversation between David Owen and John B. Howard, January 30, 1953. (Reports 003301) (Box 146)
  3 p.
  Charity organization; Philanthropy; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Interim report to the trustees: the Overseas Development Program, January 1 - June 30 (Reports 003302), 1955 (Box 146)
  15 p.
  Charity organization -- Southeast Asia; Charity organization -- Middle East; Endowments -- Southeast Asia -- Evaluation; Endowments -- Middle East -- Evaluation; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development
- Interim report to the trustees: the Overseas Development Program, July 1, 1955-March 31 (Reports 003303), 1956 (Box 146)
  12 p. + attachments: tables
  Charity organization -- Southeast Asia; Endowments -- Southeast Asia -- Evaluation; Philanthropy -- Southeast Asia; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development
- Summary of Philippine reports by Mr. E. Stanton Turner and Professor Felix Keesing (Reports 003305), 1952 (Box 147)
  Charity organization -- Philippines; Endowments -- Philippines -- Evaluation; Philanthropy -- Philippines; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- The problems of Asia and the Near East in relation to world peace (Reports 003306), 1953 (Box 147)
  36 p.
  Charity organization -- Asia; Charity organization -- Middle East; Endowments -- Asia -- Evaluation; Endowments -- Middle East -- Evaluation; Philanthropy -- Asia; Philanthropy -- Middle East; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- The Foundation and the less developed countries: The decade of the seventies (Reports 003307), 1972 (Box 147)
  Public version of a working paper originally issued in 1971.
  International Division/Office of the Vice President
  43 p.: tables
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- Developing countries; Ford Foundation. International Division
- Report on progress on Near East program (Reports 003308), 1953 (Box 147)
  Charity organization -- Middle East; Endowments -- Middle East -- Evaluation; Philanthropy -- Middle East; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Statement before Subcommittee on Technical Assistance Programs Committee on Foreign Relations - Unites States Senate (Reports 003309), 1955 (Box 147)
  Transcript of speech delivered on March 3, 1955.
  7 p. -- 28 cm
  Technical assistance; Endowments; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Summary comment: exploratory conference on land tenure and related problems (Reports 003310), 1953 (Box 147)
  Summary of conference held on December 8-9, 1952 at the Ford Foundation, New York City.
  [ii], 26 p.
  Land tenure -- Congresses; Land reform -- Congresses; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- The role of the Ford Foundation in encouraging the peaceful use of atomic energy in underdeveloped countries (Reports 003311), 1955 (Box 147)
  5 p.
  Nuclear energy -- Developing countries; Nuclear physics -- Study and teaching -- Developing countries; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Atomic energy (Reports 003312), 1955 (Box 147)
  L56-185.
  Energy policy; Nuclear energy -- Research; Nuclear energy -- Security measures; Civil defense -- United States; Radioactivity; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Proposed study of Asia (Reports 003313), 1956 (Box 147)
  Charity organization -- Asia; Philanthropy -- Asia
- Possible Ford Foundation activity in Thailand (Reports 003314), 1965
- Brazilian consultancy (May-September 1972) (Reports 003315) (Box 147)
  Ethnology -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Brazil; Anthropology -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Brazil; Ethnologists -- Training of -- Brazil; Ford Foundation. Latin America and the Caribbean
- Agricultural development in Colombia (Reports 003316), 1967 (Box 147)
  L66-134
  149 p.: tables, charts
  Agriculture -- Economic aspects -- Colombia; Economics -- Research -- Colombia; Ford Foundation. Latin America and the Caribbean
- Recommended next steps to strengthen law school, legal education, and the administration of justice (Reports 003317), 1962 (Box 147)
  Policy and Planning
  Law schools -- United States -- Finance; Law -- Study and teaching -- United States; Public interest law -- Study and teaching -- United States; Law students -- United States; Justice, Administration of -- United States; Ford Foundation. Policy and Planning
- Conference on the overseas program of the Ford Foundation August 1951. (Reports 003318) (Box 147)
  "Summary of conclusions" of conference held at Stanford University, August 24 and 25, 1951.
  4 p. + attachments
  PAPER Conference (1951 Aug. 24-25: Stanford University)
  Charity organization -- Asia; Technical assistance -- Asia; Philanthropy -- Asia; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Narrative account of visit to Ivory Coast, June 13 - June 20, 1959 (Reports 003319) (Box 147)
  File memo dated July 2, 1959.
  Overseas Division/Near East and Africa
  11 p.
  Education -- Research -- Africa; Education and state -- Africa; Ford Foundation. Near East and Africa
- Establishing centers for research, development, and application in developing countries (Reports 003320), 1970 (Box 147)
  Memo originally prepared for the Delos Symposium held in July, 1970.
  l72-236
  4 p.
  PAPER Conference (1972 June 21-21: New York, N.Y.)
  Urbanization -- Developing countries; Technology transfer -- Developing countries; Ford Foundation. Middle East and Africa
- Urban community development in India (Reports 003321), 1959
  Two-page precis included with report. Paper given at the Seminar on Urbanization in India held at the University of California, Berkeley.
  35 p.
  Urban development -- India; Population -- India; Ford Foundation. South and Southeast Asia
- Urban community development in India (Reports 003322), 1959 (Box 147)
  8 p.
  Community development, Urban -- India; Community development -- India; Urbanization -- India; Ford Foundation. South and Southeast Asia
- The rural housing wings: one year of success (Reports 003323), 1959
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- Office management; Housing
- Some problems associated with localization of the Tanganyikan Civil Service (Reports 003324), 1961 (Box 147)
  06090468
  Foundation-Administered Project (FAP)
  Consultant on manpower to the Government of Tanzania.
  Civil service -- Tanzania; Local officials and employees -- Training of -- Tanzania; Public administration -- Tanzania; Ford Foundation. Middle East and Africa
- The Foundation's Exchange of Persons Program and the Institute of International Education (Reports 003325), 1952 (Box 147)
  Draft of memo to Carl B. Spaeth, dated March 6, 1952.
  Overseas Training and Research
  Exchange of persons programs -- Finance; International relations -- Study and teaching; International education -- United States; Ford Foundation. Overseas Training and Research; Institute of International Education (New York, N.Y.)